http://amyxlu.github.io github.com/amyxlu amyxlu@cs.toronto.edu +1-647-968-6833 linkedin.com/in/amyxlu

### Summary

I am a graduate student at the Vector Institute for AI, applying computer vision and natural language processing algorithms to biological sequence data, with an emphasis on self-supervised representation learning, robustness, and interpretability. I also serve on SVAI, which organizes research collaborations of genomics/AI researchers and industry partners for understudied rare disease patients.

### **EDUCATION**

University of Waterloo

Bachelors of Science, Honours Science, Bioinformatics Option

Waterloo, Canada 2014 - 2019

University of Toronto, Vector Institute

Masters, Computer Science

Toronto, Canada 2019 - Present

#### EXPERIENCE

# University of Toronto/Vector Institute

Toronto, Canada

Masters Student — Representation learning in genomics, Dr. Alan Moses & Dr. Marzyeh Ghassemi

2019 - Present

- Natural language processing, self-supervised learning: Applying state-of-the-art word embedding models to learn robust and interpretable representations for genomic and proteomic sequences.
- Generalizability, computer vision: Benchmarked a new "paired cell in-painting" method for out-of-sample generalization in microscopy against various common computer vision algorithms (ICML 2019 Self-Supervised Learning Workshop; NeurIPS 2019 submission.)

## Harvard Medical School/Boston Children's Hospital

Boston, USA

Research Intern — Deep Learning in Clinical Genomics, Sliz Lab

2018 - Present

- Variant analysis, genotype-phenotype studies: Applying standard filtering pipelines to a whole exome (WES) dataset of epilepsy patients
- Machine learning, dimensionality reduction: Building machine learning models to classify disease phenotype from high-dimensional exome variant data, and creating a command-line interface for team members.
- **Vendor relations:** Interfaced with potential and existing third-party bioinformatics/machine learning software companies on behalf of the hospital's research computing team.

## University of Waterloo

Waterloo, Canada

Undergraduate Thesis Student — Deep Learning in Regulatory Genomics, Doxey Lab

2017 - 2018

- Convolutional neural networks in genomics: Implemented a convolutional neural network which recognizes genomic enhancers regulating femur growth with 91% accuracy (97% AUROC).
- Interpretability: Distilled biological knowledge from the "black box" network by traversing all 8-mer permutations, and reconstructing position-weighted matrices (PWMs) of "motifs" (i.e. genomic patterns) with above-threshold filter activations. All motifs found statistical matches in JASPAR (an experimentally-verified motifs database).
- Self-directed learning: Self-learned deep learning concepts and Python as a biology student.

# École polytechnique fédérale de Lausanne

Lausanne, Switzerland

Research Intern — Computational Biology, Laboratory for Biomolecular Modelling

2017

- Molecular dynamics: Contributed three potential findings on enzyme-membrane mechanisms of bacterial "superbugs" using computational simulations based on molecular dynamics (MD) principles.
- Automating workflows: Increased workflow efficiency by writing R, tcl/tk, and Csh scripts.

# University of Toronto

Toronto, Canada

Research Intern — Data Visualization in Pharmacoepidemiology, Cadarette Lab

2015 - 2017

• **Pharmacoepidemiology:** Took initiative to redesign manual workflows and exceeded expectations by contributing two co-authored publications, one first-author poster, and figures for an international epidemiology conference within two months.

• Data visualization: Wrangled data using R and SQL to create animated and interactive co-authorship networks.

### University of Toronto

Toronto, Canada

Ophthalmology Research Assistant — Statistical Analysis of Surgical Efficacy, Dr. Eric Tam

2015 - 2016

• Clinical studies, statistical analysis: Statistical analyses on the efficacy of new prophylactic procedures in femtosecond-laser assisted cataract surgery. First-author poster submitted to AAO 2016.

### SERVICE AND ACTIVITIES

- SVAI: Core Team of SVAI, a non-profit connecting patients of rare genomic diseases to the medical/AI research community and industry partners through collaborative research initiatives.
- Residence Don, Velocity Incubator: Leader for the residence program of Canada's most productive start-up incubator; fostered close relations with diverse students to support conduct and mental health crises
- Tosamaganga Hospital, Tanzania: Supported operations at a rural Tanzanian hospital and shadowed surgical procedures. Expenses were covered by scholarships, fundraising, and part-time tutoring.
- Teaching Assistant: Taught weekly tutorial lectures for a 200-level genetics course.

### AWARDS

- Canada Graduate Scholarships-Master's (CGS-M) Award: NSERC federal research grant. Valued at \$17,500.
- Scholarship of Excellence in Research: One of 13 selected by EPFL (global rank: 12). Valued at CHF 4500.
- University of Waterloo: Various entrance awards totaling \$6000.
- Associate of The Royal Conservatory (ARCT): Performer's Diploma in Piano (highest academic standing offered).

### Publications and Conference Proceedings

- Accepted: Lu AX, Lu AXP, Moses A. Paired Cell Inpainting: A Multiple-Instance Extension of Self-Supervised Learning for Bioimage Analysis. *ICML 2019 Workshop on Self-Supervised Learning*.
- Submitted: Lu AX, Lu AXP, Moses A. The Cells Out of Sample (COOS) dataset and benchmarks for measuring out-of-sample generalization of image classifiers. Submitted to NeurIPS 2019.
- Published: Ban J, Tadrous M, Lu AX, Cicinelli EA, Cadarette SM. Diffusion of indirect comparison meta-analytic methods to study drugs: a systematic review and co-authorship network analysis. *BMJ Open*.
- Under revision: Consiglio GP, Maclure M, Lu AX, Cicinelli EA, Ban JK, McCarthy L, Cadarette SM. Guidance documents for the application of Self-controlled Crossover Observational PharmacoEpidemiology (SCOPE) designs are needed: systematic review and animated co-authorship networks. Submitted to Pharmcoepi Drug Saf.

#### Posters

- Presented: Lu AX, Rockowitz S, Poduri A, Sliz P. From data to precision medicine: predictive machine learning models to uncover disease-associated variants. Poster presentation, November 2019. *Harvard Medical School BCMP Retreat 2019*.
- Presented: Lu AX, Consiglio GP, Cadarette SM. Dynamic Visualization in Co-Authorship Network Analysis. Poster presentation, August 2016. Leslie Dan Faculty of Pharmacy Undergraduate Research Symposium.
- Presented: McIlroy-Young R, Lu AX, Guenther N, Olarnyk A. A Network Analysis: Did the Arab Spring Impact the Academic Network of Tunisia Between 2010 and 2015? Poster presentation, April 2015. *Knowledge Integration Symposium*.
- Submitted: Lu AX, Tam ES. Effect of prophylactic brimonidine on subconjunctival hemorrhage in laser-assisted cataract surgery. Poster abstract. Submitted to American Academy of Ophthalmology 2017.

#### HACKATHONS AND PROJECTS

- **NLP-seq:** Used n-grams to extract features for supervised learning of function prediction, trained on Protein Data Bank data.
- Chatsense: Mobile chat app using a sentiment analysis machine learning API on voice messages and mapping dominant emotions to emojis, designed for the autistic community. Team project. Winner at YHacks at Yale.
- Alice: Web login page using a trained facial recognition model to login to online banking without passwords, designed for dementia patients. *Team project. Winner at ConUHacks III.*